OK, great.
So the first sort of paper that
I'm going to be talking about
is called emergent abilities
of large language models.
And this paper was
especially cool, I think,
because we got people
from Google and DeepMind,
and also Stanford
you might recognize
Percy, or Tatsuya, or Rishi.
I mean, we got people
to agree on what's
a nice framework of looking
at why we want to scale
and emerging abilities.
So one of the things that we've
seen throughout language models
is that you get these
predictable gains
as a result of scaling.
So here's the canonical
Kaplan et al paper,
where you can see
that, if you scale up
the size of the language
model, measured either
in compute, in data set
size, or in parameters.
You see that the loss
on the test set actually
goes down predictably.
With your screen sharing.
So people in Zoom, I don't
think, can see the slides.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Sorry.
OK.
I guess I'll say this
for the third time.
As we've seen in
language models,
if you scale up the
size of language model,
measured either in
compute, in data set size,
or a number of
parameters, you can
see that there's a sort of
this predictable improvement
in the test loss.
Now, what I'm going to
be talking about in terms
of emergence, is something
that's actually unpredictable,
if you only look at
smaller language models.
So one way that emergence has
been described in the broader
science literature
is, it's basically
seen as a qualitative
change that arises
from quantitative changes.
It sort of started with
this article in science
by a Nobel Prize
winning physicist
called "More is Different."
And I really like this post
from Jacob Steinhardt that
sort of describes emergence.
He gives a couple of
good examples here.
For example, he
says, with uranium.
With a bit of uranium,
nothing special happens.
With the large amount of
uranium packed densely enough,
you get a nuclear reaction.
And then also, with
DNA, for example.
Given only small
molecules such as calcium,
you can't meaningfully
encode useful information.
But given larger models such as
DNA, you can encode a genome.
So for this particular
work, we use this definition
of emergent abilities of large
language models in particular.
So we say that
ability is emergent
if it is not present
in smaller models,
but it is present
in larger models.
And the sort of
natural question here
is, how do you measure the size
or the scale of the language
model?
And they're traditionally
three axes of scale.
So the training FLOPS
or the amount of compute
that you use to train
the language model.
The number of model
parameters or the size
of the language model.
And also the size
of the training data
set that the model
is trained on.
And a lot of the plots here
will use either training FLOPS
or the number of
model parameters.
The reason is that the
training of the asset size
is usually fixed for
different sized models.
And because training
FLOPS is just
the data set size times
model of parameters,
you can get a similar plot
from either training FLOPS
or a number of model parameters
for most language models.
Great.
And so the first
type of emergence--
yeah, sorry, go ahead.
Yeah.
For, me it seems like it
would be relatively easier
to measure the size.
First it's like what
qualifies as natural.
I need to find chances of
natural ability versus not.
Yeah, sure--
So yeah, for example,
I'll just give an example
here, which is actually
in the next slide.
So basically, we have
this way of interacting
with language models,
called few short prompting.
And the way it works is, the
language model is a really good
next word predictor.
And when you give the
model an example, and then
you ask it for an unseen like
movie review for example.
And then you say,
what's the output?
And then here,
the language model
can say positive,
because it understands
to use the context from the
review to give the next token.
And the definition that we
use for having ability or not,
is that basically, a
few shot prompted task,
for example, sentiment
analysis, is emergent
if it has random accuracy
for small models,
but above random accuracy
for large models.
Does that make sense?
So basically, if the model isn't
doing any better than random,
then we say it doesn't
have the ability
to do this particular task.
I'll give you a
few examples here.
So here's the canonical way that
we look at plots for emergence.
So basically, what we have,
each of these different plots
is a different task, and I'll
go over some examples soon.
But the way you
read the plot is,
the x-axis is the number
of training FLOPS,
or the model scale.
And then, the y-axis
is like the accuracy,
or how good the model
is doing the task.
And then, we have different
language models from OpenAI,
from Google, and from DeepMind.
And then, each of the points
is a different language model.
It's not a language model
over the course of training.
Each point is a
different language model.
And what you see is that, for
the very small language models,
you basically get a performance
that's close to random,
or not being any
better than random.
And then once you pass
a certain threshold,
you can see that the performance
suddenly gets above random.
And this is what
we call emergence.
So basically, if you were
to extrapolate the lines
from the small
language models, you
might predict that it would
never do better than random
because it's just a flat line.
But the interesting phenomena
is that when you scale up
past a certain
threshold, you actually
do see this emergent
phenomenon where the model does
a lot better than random.
So let me go over some
concrete examples.
So here's one task.
It's basically a benchmark
called multitask NLU or MMLU.
And basically, what
it is, it's a bunch
of test questions
ranging from high school
all the way to
professional level exams.
And how it works is,
the language model
is sort of given--
for example, here is a
high school math example.
And the language model
is given a few examples,
and then for an unseen question,
it has to give the answer.
And then you can see in
the plot on the right.
So for the model scale,
if you go up to 10
to the power of
22 training slots,
you don't actually get any
better than random accuracy
on this task.
But if you scale up to 10
to the 24 training FLOPS,
then you see that all the three
models there do much better
than random accuracy.
Yeah, go ahead.
The scale of the data
used to train this,
is it roughly similar,
or because these
are different models
trained by different ports?
Yeah, the scale is, I think,
within an order of magnitude
for these models here, yeah.
And plus, every single dot
on each individual tracks
is the same data?
Yes, the data is fixed
except for a chinchilla.
Chinchilla it uses more
data for larger models,
but I believe, for all the other
models here, the amount of data
stays the same.
Yeah, here's just
another example
to show it more concretely.
So this is a task from
the BIG-bench benchmark.
Just as an aside, the BIG-bench
benchmark is 200 benchmarks,
and basically it's like a
crowdsource set of benchmarks,
so I'd recommend looking at if
you're doing [INAUDIBLE] work.
And basically, the task
is, the language model
has to take an English
sentence, and then
give the International Phonetic
Alphabet transliteration,
the IPA transliteration,
which is basically,
how to pronounce it.
And for this task,
the evaluation metric
is actually blue or like
an N-gram overlap metric.
And you got a similar
phenomenon where,
as you increase the size
of the language model,
it's flat for a while, and
then suddenly the improvement
is above random.
Great.
So I'll talk about another
interesting result here
that, that's why it's emergence.
So this was a technical
report that we put out
a couple of months ago.
And basically, there's this
really interesting prize in--
or it's like a one time
prize in language models
where, Anthropic, which
is like a startup,
basically had this prize
where, if people could come up
with a task where the
performance on the task
would actually decrease
as you increase
the size of the
language model, then you
would get a bunch of money.
So basically, there are a
lot of submissions to this,
and here's one example
of a task where
they found that the
performance would actually
decrease if you increase the
size of the language model.
So the tasks is--
here it's like, repeat
my sense is back to me,
and then the input is, all
that glisters is not glue.
And the output is--
the model has to
accurately say a glue.
And so what happened is, for
the small language model,
it doesn't know the phrase
all that glisters is not gold.
So it just copies the input
and actually does good.
It's like 100% on that.
But then, for the
medium size language
model, what you would see is
that the performance actually
decreased.
Because the medium size
language model knows the phrase
all that glisters is
not gold, and then it
says gold, which actually is
not what the task asks it to do.
Yeah, go ahead.
Someone on Zoom asked, can
you get a physical estimate
of 10 to 24 FLOPS?
Possibly in terms of training
time or number of years.
Yeah, so I think 10 to
the 24 FLOPS is around--
so at Google, we use TPUs.
And one part of TPUs, I believe,
is equal to 4,000 a 110s.
And 10 to the 24 FLOPS is like
two pods for around six weeks
or something like that.
So it's a lot of compute
to do the pretraining.
I don't know, but do you guys
remember in chemistry class,
when you'd have moles.
And it would be
like 10 to the 23,
and then you're like--
teacher would be like,
oh, don't even think about
how big this number is.
That's like the number of
floating point operations
that goes into the pretraining
of some of these models.
OK, great.
Anyways so basically, the
medium size language model
will actually do worse.
Oh, yeah.
Did you have another question?
Yeah.
Does this one the price or not?
This one is one of the--
I think it's the third
place winner or something.
[INAUDIBLE]
Because I would think--
my initial opinion
would be, oh, you
can just put a negative sign
on how you evaluate your tests
[INAUDIBLE]
What do you mean
flip a negative sign?
Well, because all of
this depends on which
evaluation scheme you use to
measure and you do your test.
So it's like the
measurement is very sparse,
you only get credit if you
do it perfectly or something.
So a lot of things emerge.
Because you just won't
get it perfectly.
Really optimize it
for a long time.
Or if you take a test,
and then like evaluate,
it's like it's minus sing.
Wouldn't it get worse?
Like something
that's [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah.
So for this thing, they
like to count it for all.
You can't just say
the task should be
able to do badly on something.
It has to be a
meaningful sort of task.
And then, I guess
your point about how
[INAUDIBLE] or the
valuation metric works
is actually a really good one.
So I guess it still
kind of counts if--
I guess the argument is,
the performance might not
look emergent if you
assign partial credit.
But we have a bunch of--
I can show example later, but
even if you use partial credit
metrics, you'll often still
see the same type of emergence.
So it's not purely a phenomenon
of not assigning partial credit
based on the valuation metric.
And then-- great.
So what we argued in this
paper is that, yeah, there
might be some tasks where
the performance starts
to decrease if you use a
medium size language model.
But if you keep scaling all
the way to the largest model
that we have at Google
that's known publicly.
PaLM.
You'll see that the
language model can actually
go back and do the
task correctly.
Because the large language
model also knows the phrase
all that glisters is not
gold, but it also understands
repeat my senses back to me.
So it's able to get
100% on this task.
So this is a different
type of emergence also.
And another class of emergence
that we talk about in the paper
is an emergent
prompting technique.
So basically, other than
[INAUDIBLE] prompting,
there's other ways
of interacting
with the language models, that
can be considered emergent.
Yeah?
Sorry, somebody
else had a question
on the previous slides.
The question is, did all
models undergo instruction fine
tuning?
None of these models
underwent instruction fine
tuning for this plot.
Yeah.
Great.
Yeah, so one way of interacting
with language models
is by basically
finding the model using
a technique called RLHF.
And basically the
way it works is,
you have this data, and humans
rate preferences for what
type of outputs they prefer.
And then the model is
trained on how to optimize
for human preferences.
And what this plot
is showing here,
is that, if you do
this RLHF on the model,
the model performance on
a different zero-shot task
actually gets worse
for small models.
You can see the blue line
is above the orange line.
Blue line is the baseline,
the orange line is RLHF.
And then, if you do
it for large models,
though, then you can see
that the performance actually
has a positive delta
from doing RLHF.
And so this is sort of an
interesting thing, where
a certain technique
might only help
if you try on a large
enough language model.
So if you only try to on
the small language models,
it'd be tough to draw
the conclusion that it
wouldn't help performance.
And then later, I'll talk about
chain of thought prompting
as another emergent problem.
So here's sort of the
hand-waving diagram
that I used, to think about
emergence as a framework.
So on the x-axis here, there's
a scale of the language model.
And on the y-axis,
there's a sort
of imaginary range of things
that a language model can do.
And then basically, you
can pick some random point,
like say, 100 billion parameters
in the language model.
And there will be
certain abilities.
OK, so first you can
see, as you increase
the size of the language model,
the number of tasks or things
the language model
can do increases.
And then you can see,
there are some tasks where
model's above 100 billion
parameters, for example,
can do them, but models below
100 parameters can't do them,
and we call these
emerging abilities
Sorry, quick question
about the slide.
What are the colors?
Oh, it's just highlighting--
the dark blue is tasks
that a smaller language
model wouldn't be able to do.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
And then, to the right
of the dotted line,
the white region of top?
Oh, that just
means tasks that we
haven't been able to solve yet
with language models, yeah.
And I'm curious to
know, do you think
that those tasks in the
white region are unsolvable,
like 100 billion scale.
Or do you think that better
models, specific training data
would allow us to have
100 billion scale get
into that white region.
Yeah, I definitely think
that it's not a fixed--
I'll give an example
shortly, but it's not a rule
that you have to have
100 billion parameters
to do a certain task.
It's just that that happens
to be the threshold that we've
observed in models so far.
And I do think, with better
training data and architecture
and algorithms, we can
probably beat that.
Cool.
Yeah, so as [INAUDIBLE]
just mentioned,
one example of getting emergence
can be with better data,
so it's not all about scale.
I'll give some [INAUDIBLE] here.
So for this task--
this is just one
of the tasks in the
BIG-bench benchmark.
You can see that for LaMDA,
which is a Google model,
and GPT-3, you actually don't
get emergence from scaling
to 137 or 175
billion parameters.
But when you come in with a
different language model, PaLM,
which is trained on better
data than LaMDA and GPT-3,
you actually can get
this emergent ability
even with the smaller
language model, so in here
at 62 billion parameters.
[INAUDIBLE] better model has
better data, or also better
architectural [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, so the challenging thing
is-- that's a great question.
There's a lot of differences
between PaLM and LaMDA,
for example.
And we can't really ablate them
in any controlled way because
of the cost of pretraining.
But our running
hypothesis is that PaLM
is trained on better
data, and that
accounts for a lot of the
difference between PaLM
and LaMDA.
I seen the smaller scales where
it is possible to ablate stuff?
Really architecture wise.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, that's a good question.
So I guess, even
here, you can look at,
for example, the
PaLM 8-billion model.
Like that.
That point there.
You can ablate it, and
it's a little bit higher,
but it's not really an
emergent yet at that point.
So it's hard to tell, for
example, this particular task,
what the effect is.
There's a question on Zoom.
Are there two different
versions of PaLM?
If not, why are there
two lines for it?
Oh, so I think the
two lines here.
One is maybe three shot,
and then one is zero shot.
Something like that.
So it just refers to
the way that we're
using the language model.
Either with or
without exemplars.
Great.
I'll talk about a small
ablation here that shows this.
So this is an ablation
on a toy task,
where basically, the language
model has to know that.
In English, you have to use
plural verbs with plural
subjects, and singular verbs
with singular subjects.
What we're doing
here is basically,
we train these small
verb models from scratch,
and then we held out--
we fixed the frequency
of certain verbs
in a training data set.
Which basically says,
OK, what's the effect
of seeing a certain verb
in the data more often?
In this plot, the x-axis is
like the frequency of the verb,
and the y-axis is
the error rate.
And what you basically
see is that, if you
have more in-domain data.
So if the model sees
the verb more times,
it does the task a lot better.
This is an example of having
high-quality data, or data
that's more in-domain for
the task evaluating on,
can make a big difference.
Even if you're fixing the
compute, the size of the model,
and the rest of the data.
Question on Zoom.
Someone asks, could
there be a way
to distill convergent
abilities down
to smaller models from
larger teacher models?
Yeah, I think so.
So larger teacher
models can basically--
you can use them, for
example, to generate data.
And then if you fine tune
the smaller model on data,
it's pretty likely that you'll
be able to get the ability
to emerge in the smaller model.
I'll talk about
example of this, too.
Let me see.
Oh actually that's
next slide, so--
Desired behaviors can be
induced in smaller models
once you know what
behavior you want.
So for example, here's a
figure from this ChatGPT paper.
And basically, the
desired behavior
here is instruction following.
And you can see that
there's multiple models.
So on the left you
have these small models
that are trained with
RLHF, and they actually
have better performance
than larger models
trained on weaker techniques.
So basically the
point is, if you
know that you want a
certain behavior that you
saw previously in an emergent
way in a larger model,
you can find a way to
fine tune on that behavior
specifically, and induce that
behavior in a smaller model.
But I guess, one
of the limitations
is that, unless you know all
the behaviors that you want,
you can't really get this
natural emergent behavior.
Yeah, another discussion
point here is that--
there's this question of, what's
the right x-axis for emergence?
So right now, we mostly
talk about model parameters
and training FLOPS.
But I guess, if you ask DeepMind
people how they look at it,
you'll get this argument that
model parameters and training
FLOPS are really just a proxy
for how good the model is.
And how good the
model is can really
be measured by perplexity or
how well it's doing on some dev
sets, which is Wiki-text 103.
So basically, you can
also measure emergence
in terms of perplexity.
So here is Wiki-text perplexity.
And then you can see,
on a downstream task
that, as the
perplexity gets better,
there's this threshold where
are you able to do a lot better
on the downstream task.
And there's a
strong correlation,
at least right now, between
perplexity and training
compute.
So you can see these two
lines are pretty similar.
Basically, I think,
in the future
if we have much
better models that
are a lot smaller, churn
out much better data
and better algorithms, then
maybe Wiki-text perplexity can
show a different type of plot
than using other metrics.
So Wiki-text is basically a--
I think it's a
subset of Wikipedia.
And then perplexity is a measure
of how well you can predict
the next word in a data set.
So basically, if you're really
good at modeling the next word
on this particular
evaluation set,
that's a measure of how well
you understand language.
That make sense?
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, this is like a
held out test set.
And then, a final
thing that I think
is pretty exciting
about emergence,
is that they're sort of not
just technical emergence
that we've talked
about, but there's
sociological changes in how
the AI community views scaling
and how to use language models.
So here are some
examples of where
scaling up the size of the
language model enables you to--
the sort of few-shot scenario.
Beat a task-specific,
fine-tuned language model
that's usually fine tuned on
say, thousands of examples.
So basically, the green line
is the prior state-of-the-art
achieved by fine tuning.
And then the blue
dots basically show,
if you take a pretrained
language model and you do
few-shot prompting, which
means the language model
isn't intentionally
trained to do the task,
you can often get
state-of-the-art results just
by continuing to scale up the
size of the language model.
And obviously, there's
limitations here,
you don't want to just keep
scaling up in order to get
state-of-the-art.
But I think it's a pretty
big change in people's minds,
that you could actually get
some of the best results
just by scaling up the
size of the language model
and doing prompting.
Question from Zoom.
Someone asks, is that
not a contradiction graph
from two or three slides ago?
Which one?
This one?
Shouldn't we, in general,
assume-- oh, he said yes.
OK.
We said, should we,
in general, assume
that scale trumps fine tune.
Yeah, so that's
a great question.
So this plot is saying that
you fine tune and you can do--
so it depends on
your particular task.
But what this plot is saying is
that fine-tuned smaller models
can do well on some tasks
if you target it well.
But for like tasks
are more complicated,
often you can do
better just by scaling.
So there's sort
of tasks that fall
into both of these categories.
And I wouldn't say that
it's contradictory.
I guess some tasks, you would do
a lot better just by scaling up
the size of the model.
And then other tasks, if
it's a very narrow domain
or the large language
model might not
be trained on that
kind of data, then you
would do better by fine tuning.
OK, great.
So here's a little
summary slide.
So basically, emergent
abilities can only
be observed in large models.
And if you try to predict
their emergence just by looking
at the plots for
small models, then you
wouldn't be able to do it.
And of had a little reflection
on how to look at this.
So emergence is
really this framing
of how to view new abilities
that are not intentionally
built in to the pretraining.
And I think the subtext for
this is super important,
which is, you can see it as
implicit argument for why
we should keep scaling
up language models
because you get these
abilities that are really
hard to find otherwise.
And the context around
this is pretty important
because it's really
expensive to continue scaling
up these models.
And even one year
ago, a lot of people
didn't believe that you could
do better on certain tasks
just by scaling up the
size of the language model.
If you work in industry
at all, there's
this interesting tension
between emergence and also
like many production tasks.
So emergence is
sort of this task
general phenomena where
you scale up the model
and it's really expensive,
but the single model
can do a lot of tasks.
In the direction of AGI.
And then, for many
production tasks,
you have the opposite where
you know what task it is.
For example, translating
into Spanish.
And then you have these
constraints on compute.
Because when you build Google
Translate, for example,
you don't want people to have
to wait a couple of seconds just
to get the translation.
And then, you also happen to
have a lot of in-domain data.
So you have, for
example, a million pairs
of English Spanish
sentences to turn on.
And this is the
opposite setting,
where you don't really care
about the model's emergence.
You can just train a very
small model on the data,
and do all of the task without
having to use a lot of compute.
And the final point
is that, I think,
a really promising
research direction,
if anyone is interested
in doing research,
is to work on predicting
future emergent abilities.
And I haven't seen
a lot of work on it
recently just because, I
think, maybe it's too hard,
for example.
You can only predict
emergence for a specific task.
Or one way of
predicting emergence
might not be super
general, and--
so I haven't seen
much work on that,
but I think this is a pretty
promising direction to work on.
And maybe [INAUDIBLE] is
working on it, I don't know.
OK, great.
Any questions on
that before I move on
to chain-of-thought prompting?
Yeah, go ahead.
Do we have any theoretical
basis to predicting
which parameters are best
scaled to get [INAUDIBLE]??
So obviously, there are many
different options for where
you [INAUDIBLE].
Like GPT, for example, you
can [INAUDIBLE] event there.
You had more of
[INAUDIBLE] or whatever.
Is that mostly
something we just test,
and then we find out
which ones scale better
to get better results--
Yeah.
I would say that we don't have
very principled methods for how
to scale up these architectures.
I'm not an expert on
this, but some of it
has to do with how
many parameters you
can fit onto a particular TPU.
But in general, I
think, you scale up
the number of intentions
heads and embeddings
somewhat proportionally.
But yeah, I think this is like
an open research question.
You can't really do ablations
over these pretraining.
You can't really do
ablations over pretraining.
It's hard to have any
principled way of doing it,
other than some engineers who
are in charge of doing it.
Say, OK, I think this is
the right thing to do,
and then it kind of
works, and you go with it.
Yeah?
Do you have any indication
of [INAUDIBLE] behavior
of the [INAUDIBLE]?
Do you expect that
eventually it would reach
a plateau of [INAUDIBLE] loss?
Or would it just go all
the way down to zero?
Yeah, that's a great question.
You mean on perplexity or some--
on a particular task,
or just in general,
like next word prediction?
Well, seems like these results
are pretty general, pretty task
independent, right?
It's like emergent scaling.
Yeah.
But if you take the limit
of infinite parameters,
then even analytically,
is there any sense
of how that converges?
Yeah, I have no clue.
For most of these tasks, there's
a limit to accuracy, like 100%,
for example.
So there's some sort
of asymptote there.
But I guess, the deeper question
that you might be asking is,
can a language
model perfectly know
how to predict the next
word for any given input?
And maybe, I guess
there's some limit to--
if I say a sentence, there
are two possible next words
or something, and
you might not be
able to guess that perfectly.
I think there's
some limit, but I
think we're far from
reaching that limit,
and there's still a
lot of unsolved tasks
that sort of indicate that
there's a lot of headroom.
Yeah?
If researchers are interested
in studying divergence,
what family of
different-sized models
is publicly available,
or best for study units?
Yeah, good question.
So I think the OpenAI API
has a lot of language models,
and we actually use that a lot.
Even at Google, it's
used to study emergence.
And that's one way of doing it.
And actually, a lot of these
models are currently free.
They're rate limited,
but they're free,
so we also use that.
I think there's also
smaller language models.
Like, for example, there's
the UL2 model, that's
like 20 billion parameters.
But I guess--
you're right, there
is this challenge where
small language models,
you won't see a lot of
these emergent behaviors.
So you kind of have
to either train--
yeah, so you have to either
use OpenAI API for now,
or wait until people
train larger models.
I guess, there's also the BLOOM
and like-- you guys probably
know of that.
The OPT models that
are publicly available,
but I haven't seen a lot
of experiments on them.
Yeah.
Yeah?
So my question is, are there
emergent abilities that are
accessible and lower parameter
[INAUDIBLE] maybe there might
be some that are-- maybe
not like chain of thought,
but I heard some that are like--
Yeah, definitely, I
think, in the paper
we had a list couple
of dozen abilities
that would be emerging on
like 8 billion parameters,
or like $60 billion parameters
or something like that.
I have two questions from Zoom.
The first question is, do
you see strategy tactics
between the larger tech firms
differing systematically
in studying these models?
Or is basically everyone
taking the same approach?
I wouldn't say that everyone
is taking the same approach.
I think, as one
example, Anthropic
takes a very
safety-centric approach.
And they're super interested
in emergent abilities
because there could be emergent
abilities that are undesirable,
and they want to predict
those types of things.
also don't know what
happens at other companies
other than at Google, so I can't
really speak too much to that.
Yeah?
The second question.
What are some examples of tasks
or abilities that have not yet
emerged even models like
LaMDA, ChatGPT, et cetera?
Oh, yeah, I have--
maybe I'll just show
this real quick.
There's a nice list somewhere.
Yeah, so basically,
what we did is,
there's 200 tasks in BIG bench.
And then we basically
classified them
into smoothly increasing,
emergent with GPT-3 or LaMDA,
emergent with PaLM,
and then flat,
which is no model
better than random.
So I think, if you look at
any of these tasks here,
they should still
not have emerged yet.
And if you can get them to
emerge, that'd be interesting.
Sorry?
I think ChatGPT could
be 20 questions.
Oh, OK, yeah, this
is not a super--
I think this is a couple
of months old, so--
Oh, sorry.
Yeah, yeah.
Oh, 20 questions?
OK, yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, I think--
the cool thing is,
you can see over time, right?
Originally, maybe only
these were emerging.
And then when PaLM
came out, you'd
see a couple of dozen more
abilities emerging and then--
I suspect, in a year
or two, most of these
will become emergent, and
we'll need harder benchmarks.
Yeah?
There's another
question on Zoom.
Why doesn't Google take as much
of a safety-centric approach,
like you said in Anthropic does?
Are there reasons to believe
harmful capabilities wouldn't
be emergent?
Yeah, I don't want to answer the
question on behalf of Google,
I just can only talk
about my own opinions.
But I think the
reality is that Google,
even if you look at the amount
of research that Google does,
it might not be in the
large language model space
specifically.
But the amount of safety
research that we do, I think,
is more than Anthropic,
if you actually
look at the number
of papers published.
Don't quote me on this,
but I think that's correct.
OK.
Great.
So yeah, I'll talk about
chain-of-thought prompting.
So basically,
chain-of-thought prompting
is this way of doing
reasoning, multi-step reasoning
with large language models.
And yeah, I wanted
to say that I get
super exciting to
see a lot of people
at Google working on this, and
also to see Sundar, our CEO,
present this at our last
year's Google I/O press event.
And basically, the
motivation for this
is that we want language models
to do more complicated tasks
that--
for example, we
know language models
can do easy tasks like
[INAUDIBLE] analysis
or translation.
But what about more
complicated tasks
that might even take a human
a minute or more to do?
And the goal here is
to basically guide them
with metadata.
So for example, instead of just
giving an input-output pair,
we want to give them the
entire reasoning process,
and have them mimic that.
And basically, you can see
here, in a standard prompt,
you have the question
and then the answer,
and then you have a
question, and the model
gives a new answer.
Unfortunately it's wrong.
And then, with
chain-of-thought prompting,
you give the model
a question, and then
like how your teacher would
ask you to show your work,
you give the chain
of thought, is
what we call it, or
basically, a reasoning path.
And then you give
the final answer.
And then when the model
sees this unseen question,
now it's able to give
the reasoning path,
and then give the
correct final answer.
And the way that we add these
prompts into the prompt,
is basically, we just
manually write a couple,
and then add it into the prompt.
So let me just show
how that works.
So this is the OpenAI API.
And basically, here's the
non-chain-of-thought way
of doing it.
So basically, you would have
a question, answer, question,
answer, question, answer.
And then a new question about--
cafeteria has 23
apples, they use 20
to make lunch and
about six more.
How many apples they have?
And the model gets it wrong.
And the only difference
with chain of thought
is that you give these
intermediate reasoning paths
before giving the final answer.
So here's a path.
There's a reasoning chain.
There's another reasoning chain.
And then, now the model
for this unseen question
gives the entire
reasoning process.
And then this actually enables
the models to get it correct.
I'll give another quick example.
This one.
So here the task is, just
take the last letters
of the words of Bill Gates.
So L from Bill and S from gates.
And then concatenate them.
And the answer should be LS.
And then here, the
model gets it wrong.
The answer should be NK.
It says SK.
And then, if you do
chain of thought,
obviously it becomes
very easy for the model.
So it says the last third
of Bill L, the last letter
of Gates is S. Answer is LS.
And then here, it's able to do,
the last letter of Elon is N,
and the last letter of
Musk is K, and answers NK.
Is this clear?
Any questions about
what's going on here?
OK.
So basically, we can have
these similar plots where
the x-axis is the model scale,
the y-axis is the performance.
So on the left, we have this
math word question benchmark
called GSMAK.
It's basically
questions that you'd
see in an elementary
school math test.
And you can see, the
blue dot is standard,
and the purple star
is chain of thought.
Basically, you see that
the chain of thought,
if you use a large enough
model, does a lot better
than standard prompting.
And actually, it beats
the fine-tuned state
of the art at the time.
A similar example is on this
benchmark called StrategyQA.
And what StrategyQA
is it's basically
like this world knowledge
plus common-sense reasoning
benchmark.
So the question would
be like, can you
hide a basketball in
the sand cats ear?
And then the model would say, a
basketball is about this size,
a sand cat's ear is that,
so it would not fit.
And on this benchmark,
you can also
see that we can beat the
fine-tuned state of the art
from before, just by
using chain of thought
with a large enough
language model.
So one way we use this is that
we evaluate a chain of thought
on a certain subset
of BIG-bench tasks.
So we created the subset
called BIG-bench hard.
And basically, it's like
23 challenging tasks
from BIG-bench, where
no model had done better
than the average human writer.
So the way that you
prompt the model
is that you'd have a task
description, question, options,
chain of thought.
And then the test
[AUDIO OUT] question.
And so I'll give a couple
of examples of tasks here.
So one example is navigate.
Basically, what
the language model
has to do in this task is it
has to basically follow these--
so the question is, if you
follow these instructions,
do you return to
the starting point?
Turn left, turn right, take
five steps, take four steps,
turn around and take nine steps.
And then, the model following
the [INAUDIBLE] exemplars
is able to basically track
state after all of the actions.
And then at the end it says,
OK, are we at the final answer--
are we at the original location?
If it is zero, zero,
then the answer is yes.
Just to give an example
of another task.
Here's a task that's
very easy for humans,
basically word sorting.
So there's a list of words.
Early, bela, I'm not
going to read them.
And basically, the
model has to sort them
in alphabetical order.
And here, the model can follow
the [INAUDIBLE] exemplar.
So you have this pretty
complicated chain of thought,
where the model has to
sort each of the subparts,
and then finally, it gets to the
final answer, which is correct.
So here's this result summary
on this subset of BIG-bench.
So you can see, OK,
we have two metrics.
One is just the average
performance on all these tasks,
and the second is
percent of tasks that are
above the average human writer.
So average human writer is
67, max human writer is 94.
And then prior results, the
model was doing way worse.
It was like 50.
And this is sort of by
construction of the subset.
And then we use
DaVinci 0.2, which is
like one of the open AI models.
And actually you can use this
one for free with OpenAI API.
And basically, if you
do answer only prompting
without chain of
thought, then you sort of
are being the average
human writer on 5 of 27.
But if you use
chain-of-thought prompting,
then the performance increases
by this pretty decent amount,
and you're able to pass
the average human--
on the majority of tasks.
And then below is just
this visualization
of the tasks that are doing
worse than humans, in red,
and then better
than humans in blue.
Yeah?
Two questions.
One is, isn't this
similar to [INAUDIBLE],,
in spirit at least?
Is what similar?
I think chain-of-thought prompt,
I'm not sure what [INAUDIBLE]
in chain of thought.
Yeah, I think it's--
I wouldn't call it similar.
So train of thought
is basically,
you take a pretrained
language model,
and you use a prompting
technique that includes
intermediate reasoning path.
The way that RLHF works is that
you have this additional data
that you want to fine
tune the model on,
and you have a
preference model that
predicts how well does
a certain output--
how likely is that to
be preferred by humans?
And then RLHF, what that
does is it fine tunes
the language model to do
well on the preference models
prediction.
So basically, it's sort
of aligning the model
with what humans would prefer.
Is there a second question?
Yeah, I'm sorry, it's here.
Grace asks, can chain of thought
be encoded in fine tuning,
rather than having to
be in the [INAUDIBLE]??
Yes.
The short answer is yes.
The sort of complicated
thing about that
is that you have to have
chain-of-thought intermediate
steps.
And those are pretty--
it can be costly to gather that
data and to do the fine tuning.
One last question.
Sorry for everybody.
Another student
asks, do you think
that chain-of-thought and
prompt engineering in general
is just an artifact
that won't be
necessary for
larger-scale models that
are able to understand
the [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah, so that's
a great question.
Basically, the question is, how
ephemeral is prompt engineering
going to be?
I think we'll find out,
but some initial intuitions
are, for easy tasks that
are easy to describe,
and maybe they're
multiple choice,
larger models will
probably be more
robust to prompt
engineering, and there's
less you can do with that.
But I think, as language
models get more powerful,
it'll sort of be more
normal to use them
on a lot more challenging tasks.
And in those tasks, you'll have
to specify exactly what you
want them all to do et cetera.
So I think there will
still be some room
for prompt engineering there,
at least in the near future.
Yeah, go ahead.
Do you know how well does
chain-of-thought prompting
[INAUDIBLE].
And so for example, if you
show these two tasks write
a simple [INAUDIBLE],, and
then the other one basically
sorting the words
alphabetically.
So I mean, I see
that [INAUDIBLE]
if you have to give the
chain of thought or something
worse or better?
Yeah, that's a great question.
So for some tasks where
you've seen similar data
in pretraining, the
model can do really well,
even if the chain of thought
is from another task.
So for example, like
math word problems.
You actually don't really
need a math chain of thought.
Because the model already
knows how to do that.
But for a task like
this, you probably
haven't seen any data that's
like the chain of thought here.
So without
task-specific exemplars,
you probably wouldn't do
super well on tasks like this
without manually writing
them for other examples.
Yeah?
I'm wondering, as the
researcher behind this.
What mental model would we use?
Like you can try,
and it's like, do
you perceive the model as
like-- if I was in person,
how would I do this better?
Or is it like trying to give
it more compute in order to--
people are guessing the answer?
Yeah, great question.
I think my motivation
was just thinking
about it, just as you said.
What's going on
in a human's mind
while they try to solve
this math question?
And well, if you notice,
at least some humans
will think actually
in natural language.
So if you just think about it.
If you pay attention a lot to
what's going on in your mind,
you actually notice
that sometimes you
think in language.
And so while the language model
can think of language, too.
So that was kind of the
motivation behind asking
the language model to do that.
And I think, one
thing that went well
is that the development
of this technique
actually coincided with
the development of PaLM.
And so-- yeah, basically,
having the model PaLM
sort of allowed us to
do a lot better task--
or a lot more challenging
tasks using chain of thought.
Yeah?
So when talking about
the [INAUDIBLE]..
We're saying that it matters
that the absolute number
of examples of this
chain-of-thought process
or whatever, in the data set.
Or in [INAUDIBLE].
Is that the main
significant thing,
or is it relative
number of frequency
of those examples, or
just negative examples,
which are not good
examples of how
to do those as much as
just the absolute number
of good examples?
Yeah good question.
So I guess the challenging
thing is, we can't really
measure how many similar
examples are in the training
set.
It's hard to do that
well, and I don't think
anyone has done that before.
So it's this open question
of why a chain of thought
even works.
Because you actually
don't see similar data
like that in the training set.
Yeah, I think it's open
question like why it works.
[INAUDIBLE] chain of thought.
I want to see [INAUDIBLE]
thinking about how [INAUDIBLE]
things.
That sometimes you
think in language,
and that model
should do that, too.
But like how do you
actually think in--
like what a [INAUDIBLE]
model like--
I mean, is that like a shift
in very a specific task,
like some way to get more
focus from [INAUDIBLE]??
How do you think about it?
Yeah, I don't really
think about it
in terms of what's going
on in the weights, I guess,
the way that I think
about it is that like--
it'd be unfair for me to
give you a math question,
and ask you to give me the
answer within like half
a second.
Which is basically what
you're doing with the model,
and when you do a chain
of thought, right?
You're basically asking
this challenging question,
and the model
doesn't have enough
compute to solve it in
one pass to give you
the next answer immediately.
I think the second
thing that I think
about is that the
model has learned
a compositional set of
skills during pretraining,
so maybe it hasn't
really learned
this particular navigate
task during pretraining.
But certain other things, right?
OK, if you take five steps and
you're facing this, maybe yeah,
you should add five here or
something like that, right?
And it's learned how
to do pattern matching.
So maybe in the
[INAUDIBLE] exemplars,
it can match sort of what
the reasoning path is
with what the question was.
And there's these little skills
that the model might know.
And then maybe if you
can combine them together
in some clever way, then
you can get them all
to solve a more
challenging problems.
How much time do we have?
We have a half hour.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
OK, 50.
OK OK.
OK, great.
That's a good example of
how we judge these tasks.
Same way.
A bunch of different answers,
all of them [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah.
OK, great.
Yeah, feel free to keep asking
questions if you have any.
So yeah, here's another
example of emergence.
So basically, you can see,
there's three models here
in GPT, Codex and PaLM.
Chain of though in blue non
chain of thought is in gray.
And then you can
see, you actually
have to have sufficient model
scale to chain of thought
to work well.
And I guess, the
intuition here is
that, if you have a
really small model,
the model will keep
repeating itself or not
saying anything
coherent, and never
give you a final answer, which
is why using chain of thought
for the small models
doesn't really work well.
And then for the large models,
obviously, for multi problems,
the model is going
to be able to solve
the task at a lot higher
accuracy with chain of thought.
And another cool thing
about chain of thought
is, there are some tasks
where you sort of wouldn't
get emergent behavior at all.
So emergence hasn't
been unlocked yet.
But you can see that if
you use chain of thought,
you can unlock this emergent
performance in smaller models.
So one example here is
multi-step arithmetic, where--
I don't know if you'll ever--
I don't want to say never.
But it's hard to imagine
a model getting this.
Here's a question and then
the next token is correct.
That's pretty hard
to solve in one step.
But with chain of thought you
can get 50% accuracy on this
just by having the model output
these intermediate reasoning
steps.
So I have a question.
Oh, yeah.
Is this something that needs
a rehab intuition about what's
going on?
Abstractly, I know that a
transformer can definitely
do addition.
[INAUDIBLE] right?
In one step.
But it can take in the
numbers and do the carries--
Definitely, yeah, yeah.
But then there's this question
of what happens empirically,
right?
And I understand that it isn't
necessarily a lot of space
to do arithmetic.
So my question is, how--
can you really tell
the difference?
Maybe [INAUDIBLE] ways to tell
the difference between things
that have an emerge because
there's just no space.
Or there's so many
tasks that you're
allotted, any space specifically
do that one, versus the task
is so hard that it just
can't, even if you like--
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] they're
trying to do it.
Yeah, that's a good question.
I think-- there seems to be some
subset of tasks where it just
doesn't fit well with the way
that we train language models.
So for example, in language
models, we use tokens, right?
And so if you give
it the token four,
it actually doesn't
take the number four,
it takes this embedding
that's like 1,000
dimensions or something.
Or if you give it a word and ask
it to reverse like the letters.
This is a super easy task,
but the way we train the model
doesn't actually look at
the letters and stuff.
So I think there's a certain
subset of tasks where
it doesn't really just
fit well with the way
that we train transformers,
and you can actually--
I mean, if you really
care about these tasks,
you can just solve them using
code or something like that.
But yeah, I don't think
this is really an inherent--
something that would never
emerge, because it's too hard.
Yeah.
Yeah?
We have a question on Zoom.
Also, by the way, sorry,
I forgot to mention.
Somebody's asking, can
you repeat the questions?
Because they can't always hear--
Oh, OK.
Yeah.
That's my bad.
It's my bad.
So the question someone
asked is, do you
think chain of thought would
be a viable interpretability
technique for very
advanced AI systems?
And they mentioned that there
is some research by Anthropic
called externalized reasoning
oversight by Tamera Lanham.
Will it be a viable
interpretability technique
for advanced AI?
Yeah, am I supposed
to repeat this?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, sorry.
Oh, so the question is,
can chain of thought
be a viable interpretability
technique for AI?
I think there's no guarantee
that the chain of thought
is how the model actually
arrives at the final answer.
But often, you can
use it to debug like,
why isn't the model getting
this question correct.
Or what can we do better
in the chain of thought
to help them all
get this correct?
I haven't read the Anthropic
paper that was mentioned,
so I actually don't
know the answer to that.
OK.
Another interesting
result that we had here
was that you can actually
do like multi-lingual
chain-of-thought prompting.
And so basically
what we had is, we
translated this benchmark
of math word problems
to 10 languages.
And then we prompt the model
to do it in, say, Bengali.
And then the model
has to basically do
the math problem in Bengali
and give the final answer.
I think the cool
thing about this
is, this input is like
highly improbable, right?
So Bengali is 0.1% of
the pretraining data,
and math word
problems are probably
even smaller subset of that.
And basically, the
interesting thing is,
the model can actually do these
types of questions pretty well.
To probably a surprising degree.
So if you ask people before, I
show them this result. How well
can the model do like these
math questions in Swahili?
Probably like 10%.
But actually, even very
underrepresented languages
like Swahili, or Bengali, or
Telugu, and Thai, the model
can do surprisingly well,
despite the fact that they only
occupy a very small subset
of the pretrained data.
Yeah?
Actually speaking to this, and
most of my experience with this
is ChatGPT.
But if you ask things
in different languages,
despite not being explicitly
trained in these languages,
right?
It seems have derived
reasoning, independent
of language to some extent.
Do the reasoning--
it's kind of funny,
sometimes it always
looks like it
does the reasoning in English,
and then translates back
to the other language.
The answers it gives
you a sort of--
if you reason to
English, and then
translate to the other thing.
So do you think that learning
the structure of a language
and learning reasoning
abilities are
somewhat separate in
large language models?
Or that it inherently will
learn creative thought reasoning
within that language within
the structure of the language,
like the way thought
works in that language?
Did that make sense?
Yeah, that's a great question.
I'm not sure how
to measure that,
but I've definitely
thought about it.
I think the language--
I mean based on these
results, you probably
didn't have any math questions
in Swahili for the model
to learn from.
And I think definitely there's
something language agnostic
going on, where the model
learns reasoning independently
of language, and then
it can express it
in different languages
if it needs to.
Yeah, but I don't think anyone--
I don't think we know
the answers to that yet.
Yeah, so basically, one question
that comes up frequently
is, why does scaling up
improve chain-of-thought?
And one way of
looking at this is,
we can take a smaller
model like PaLM-62B
and see what types of errors
are fixed from scaling
up to 540 parameters.
And you see that for these
three categories that we came up
with, some of all
of them get fixed.
So scaling seems to have
this universal effect
on improving different types
of errors from smaller models.
And then here's
this the [INAUDIBLE]
diagram that express
in different ways.
So basically, you
have some tasks
that are doable with
standard prompting.
So in blue.
And then the goal of
chain-of-though prompting
is to increase the set
of tasks that we can do.
So for example, now
the ones shown in pink
include math word problems,
symbolic reasoning,
and challenging common
sense reasoning, yeah.
One more question.
Have you done any calculations
to figure out how much--
is any of this contribution
just because of the fact
that you do more computations
when you put in longer prompts.
Like you put multiple
passes through the model,
you create multiple
embeddings to adjust
the things the model's
looking at in a way.
How much of that--
have you tried
non-chain-of-thought prompts
with like same token lengths?
Yeah, yeah, we tried with
x, x, x, x, x or something,
and it doesn't work.
I see.
So I think it's not
just about the compute,
I think it's about the language
guiding the model as part
of the reasoning.
I see.
And have you tried describing
the problem in more detail?
[INAUDIBLE]
I'm just very curious about--
sounds like a very
interesting property,
and I'm very curious
exactly how it fits in.
Yeah, you mean like describing
the question in three
different ways and saying--
Yeah, just explaining the
question in more detail,
instead of explicitly doing
the step-by-step thing,
and seeing how that--
Yeah.
I haven't tried that,
but I would be surprised
if that worked.
Yeah.
Or you could edit the
question you need,
Did you try having it--
I'll put the answer and
then explain its reasoning,
and did that?
Yeah, that doesn't work as well.
Yeah.
But it depends on the task also.
So like-- Yeah.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
That seems to be the case, yeah.
Yeah?
Does there really
have to be reasoning?
I mean, you like just
[INAUDIBLE] or that's
your calculation.
Sort of [INAUDIBLE] the answer.
In a way, you can [INAUDIBLE].
Chain of thought is like
a very structured thing.
What if the same
structures [INAUDIBLE]
we use them for random things
Yeah.
You could try it.
I'd be surprised if it works.
I think like
outputting tokens is
pretty important for the model.
OK.
So we're doing on time.
OK, great.
So the last part I think
is a pretty cool trick
with chain of thought.
So basically, what
people usually do is,
they'll just generate
one chain of thought,
and then they'll take
the final answer.
But there's this nice trick
called self consistency, where
you can use temperature
sampling with the model
to generate a bunch
of different reasoning
paths and final answers.
And then if you just
take a majority vote
over the final answers, this
ends up improving performance
by a pretty big margin, so--
for example, here,
you can see on GSMAK,
which is like the math
word problem data set.
The improvement goes from--
the performance is 56.
And then if you do
self consistency,
that becomes 74, which is
a pretty big improvement.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Here how many are the averaging
number for self consistency?
I think 40.
So it increases the cost of
the inference type compute,
but improves
performance by a lot.
You might be about to answer
this, but I'm curious to know.
How many samples
or how many chains
does one need to draw
to get a significant--
what is the trade off
if the number of chains
averaged over performance gain.
I think it depends on the--
sorry, the question
is, how many chains
do you need to get
performance gain?
I think the answer really
depends on the data set.
But usually, you can get
something good with 16 I think.
Yeah.
I'm sorry we have a question.
How does the temperature
change the way a model works.
OK.
The question is, how
does the temperature
change the way the model works.
Basically, when you use
temperature decoding,
the language model
can stochastically
pick one of the outputs, instead
of always picking the highest
probability next word.
So basically, you get these
more stochastic outputs
that are still based on what
the language model has learned,
but it's just a little
bit more random.
And then, finally,
self consistency also
seems to be emergent ability.
I guess part of it is
because chain of thought
is emerging because
you wouldn't get
any better than random
performance without doing train
of thought.
But yeah, you kind
of see this big delta
from self consistency
for larger models.
Great.
So I'm going to run out of time.
Let me just go to--
I'll just talk about
this a little bit.
So I think, in addition
to just purely scaling
up the language model, which
is only available to people
in the industry.
I think there's a couple
of interesting directions
to work on.
One is better prompting
and characterization
of language model abilities.
I think right now,
we're sort of just
at the edge of knowing what
the best way to prompt language
models is.
There's also pretty
good applied work.
So you can use
language models, I've
heard, to train therapists.
To help with creative
writing, to help with science.
I think ChatGPT has really
shown what language models can
do in this regard.
I think benchmarks
are also something
that's pretty lacking.
Because I think we solve
benchmarks pretty quickly.
For example PaLM beat the
average human on BIG-bench
within a year or something
of a BIG-bench coming out.
So I think we need
more benchmarks,
I think that's going to be
an important contribution.
And then the final
one is, how can we
have computer-efficient methods
to make language models better,
so that it's less
expensive to use them,
and more people get to use them.
Great.
So I'll end here.
And feel free to email me
if you have any feedback,
and if you're
interested in Google,
feel free to
[INAUDIBLE] as well.
Thanks.
Thank you.